Irene Balelli

Ph.D.

Inria Sophia Antipolis, Epione Team 2004 Route des Lucioles. 06902 Valbonne, France @ 0033 602082747 ⊠ irene.balelli@inria.fr ibalelli.github.io



Biographical Information

November 3, 1988, in Forlimpopoli - Italy.

Italian. Citizenship

Marital status Under PACS.

Family Two children (2015 and 2018).

situation

Research Interests

Modeling/ Bayesian Statistics. Latent variable models. Generative models. Mixed effects models. Identifiability Statistics analysis. Sensitivity analysis. Parameter estimation with population approach. Expectation

Maximization. PK/PD. In-silico trials

Federated learning. Distributed learning. Machine

Learning

Data Differential privacy. Large-scale heterogeneous biomedical data. Missing data.

governance

Biomedical Neurodegenerative diseases: Alzheimer Disease. Parkinson Disease. Imaging data.

Applications Immunology: Immune response dynamics. Immune system. Antibody affinity maturation. B-cells.

Immune memory. Vaccination.

Applied Random walks on graphs. Markov chains. Graph theory. Galton-Watson processes. Evolutionary

Probability landscapes

Current Position

2021-now Research scientist (ISFP) in mathematical modeling for computational biomedicine, EPI-

ONE team - Centre Inria d'Université Côte d'Azur, Valbonne - France.

Experience

2020-2021 Post-doctoral research fellowship in federated statistical learning for new generation metaanalyses of large-scale and secured biomedical data, EPIONE team - Inria Sophia Antipolis

Méditerranée, Valbonne - France.

2017-2019 Post-doctoral research fellowship in modeling of the immune response to Ebola vaccine,

SISTM team - Inserm U1219 Bordeaux Population Health, Bordeaux - France.

Education

2013–2016 PhD in Applied Mathematics with teaching activities, LAGA - Université Paris 13, Villetaneuse

Title: Mathematical foundations of antibody affinity maturation.

Supervisors: Vuk Milišić, Gilles Wainrib, Hatem Zaag.

Defense date: November 30, 2016.

- 2011–2013 Master Degree in Mathematics Applied to Biology and Medicine, Master thesis: A mathematical model of somatic hypermutation (Supervisors: V. Milišić, G. Wainrib), Université Paris 6, Paris France.
- 2010-2011 Erasmus Program, Universidad Complutense, Department of Mathematics, Madrid Spain.
- 2007–2010 **Bachelor degree in Mathematics**, *Bachelor thesis:* Il modello di Bressloff e Cowan: allucinazioni visive come stati stabili di attivazione corticale (*Supervisor: G. Citti*), Universitá di Bologna, Bologna Italy.

Papers and Preprints

- **I. Balelli**, S. Silva, M. Lorenzi., *A Differentially Private Probabilistic Framework for Federated Heterogeneous Multi-View Datasets Variability*, Journal of Machine Learning for Biomedical Imaging (MELBA). 2022:012.
- **I. Balelli**, S. Silva, M. Lorenzi., *A Probabilistic Framework for Modeling the Variability Across Federated Datasets of Heterogeneous Multi-View Observations*, International Conference on Information Processing in Medical Imaging. Springer, Cham, 2021. p. 701-714..
- Q. Clairon, C. Pasin, **I. Balelli**, R. Thiébaut, M. Prague., *Parameter estimation in nonlinear mixed effect models based on ordinary differential equations: an optimal control approach*, [arXiv: 2102.11543].
- M. Prague, J. Gerold, **I. Balelli**, C. Pasin, J. Li, D. Barouch, J. Whitney, A. Hill., *Viral rebound kinetics following single and combination immunotherapy for HIV/SIV*, [bioRxiv 700401; doi: https://doi.org/10.1101/700401].
- **I. Balelli**, C. Pasin, M. Prague, F. Crauste, T. Van Effelterre, V. Bockstal, L. Solforosi, R. Thiébaut, A model for establishment, maintenance and reactivation of the immune response after vaccination against Ebola virus, Journal of Theoretical Biology, 2020, DOI: 10.1016/j.jtbi.2020.110254.
- C. Pasin, **I. Balelli**, T. Van Effelterre, V. Bockstal, L. Solforosi, M. Prague, M. Douoguih, R. Thiébaut, *Dynamics of the humoral immune response to a prime-boost Ebola vaccine: quantification and sources of variation*, Journal of Virology, 2019, **DOI:** 10.1128/JVI.00579-19.
- **I. Balelli**, V. Milišić, G. Wainrib, *Multi-type Galton-Watson processes with affinity-dependent selection applied to antibody affinity maturation*, Bulletin of Mathematical Biology, 2019, vol. 81, no 3, p. 830-868.
- **I. Balelli**, V. Milišić, G. Wainrib, *Random walks on binary strings applied to the somatic hypermutation of B-cells*, Mathematical Biosciences, 2018, vol. 300, p. 168-186.
- **I.** Balelli, V. Milišić, G. Wainrib, *Branching random walks on binary strings for evolutionary processes in adaptive immunity*, [arXiv: 1607.00927].

Attended Conferences, Meetings and Seminars

- 2021 Information Processing in Medical Imaging (IPMI) 2021, Poster, Online event.
- 31A Scientific Days, Poster, Nice France.Sophl.A Summit 2020, Talk, Sophia Antipolis France.
- 2019 4th EBOVAC1/2 Annual meeting, *Talk*, Nairobi Kenya. VRI Annual meeting, *Talk*, Paris France.
- 2018 IMI 10^{th} Anniversary Scientific Symposium, Talk, 3^{rd} committee prize "best presentation", Brussels Belgium.
 - **CROI 2018**, Poster (J.M. Gerold, C. Pasin, I. Balelli, S. Lim, C. Osuna, J.B. Whitney, D.H. Barouch, M. Prague, A.L. Hill), Boston United States.
 - 3rd EBOVAC1/2 Annual meeting, Talk (shared with C. Pasin), Amsterdam Nederland.
- 2017 Systems Immunology and Vaccine design, Heidelberg Germany.
- 2016 **Probabilities and Statistics seminar (LAGA)**, *Talk*, Villetaneuse France. **1st Challenges in inflammation meeting**, Florence Italy.

Les probabilités de demain, Talk, IHÉS - Bures-sur-Yvette - France.

Summer school: "PDE and Probability for Life Sciences", Poster, CIRM - Marseille - France.

- 2015 EDP-Normandie, Poster, Havre France.
- 2014 **InflaConf: Mathematical modeling in immunology and inflammation**, *Talk*, Paris France. **CANUM 2014**, *Poster*, Carry-le-Rouet France.

Inflamex day, Talk, CIEP Sèvres - France.

2013 GDR Métice: Inflammation and Treatment Resistance, Talk, Lyon - France.

Thematic schools

- 2022 **Al4Health Winter School**, *Workshop:* Fed-BioMed, an open source framework for federated learning in real world healthcare applications, Online event.
- 2021 **Al4Health Winter School**, *Workshop:* Handling heterogeneity in the analysis of biomedical information, Online event.

First Inria-DFKI European Summer School on Artificial Intelligence, *Workshop:* Federated learning methods and frameworks for collaborative data analysis, Online event.

Teaching Activities

2020-2022 **Bayesian learning**, *Lectures and tutorials*, M2 MSc Data Science & Artificial Intelligence, University Côte d'Azur.

Sophia Antipolis - France

Modeling of biological systems, Lectures and tutorials, M2 BIM, University Côte d'Azur.

Nice - France

Analysis and Modeling, Tutorials, 1st year bachelor's degree, University Côte d'Azur.

Nice - France

2013-2016 **Probability and Statistics 2**, *Tutorials*, 2nd year bachelor's degree in Mathematics and MIEF, University Paris 13.

Villetaneuse - France

Probability and Statistics 1, *Tutorials*, 2nd year bachelor's degree in Mathematics, University Paris 13.

Villetaneuse - France

Probability and Statistics, *Tutorials*, 1st year Engineering degree (Apprentissage énergétique), Engineering School Sup Galilée.

Villetaneuse - France

Statistics, *Tutorials*, 1st year Engineering degree MACS (Mathématiques Appliquées et Calcul Scientifique), Engineering School Sup Galilée.

Villetaneuse - France

Probability, Tutorials, 2nd year IUT-Info, University Paris 13.

Villetaneuse - France

Inferential statistics, Tutorials, 2nd year DUT-GEA, University Paris 13.

Bobigny - France

Softwares

Fed-BioMed Open-source federated learning framework: fedbiomed.gitlabpages.inria.fr

Computer Skills

Programming Python, Matlab, R Languages

Operating Mac 0SX, Linux, Windows Systems

Parameter estimation softwares

Editing & Office Office, LATEX

Office

Numerical Stochastic processes, Monte Carlo methods, ODE system (simulation / sensitivity analysis)

Others

Languages

ItalianMother tongueEnglishFluentFrenchbilingualSpanishFluent